hi good morning and welcome back to the
alarm room
and i don't know us
people at diamond mountain are feeling
really happy i don't know why
i don't know just being here and
we worked very hard yesterday to talk
about how we could get ready for
having you guys come here maybe in
october late october uh if the virus
goes well
so i think it might be possible so i
hope so
get your vaccinations okay all right
and okay we
are in chandi kirti so master chandi
kirti
so we took a trip uh to master chandi
kiriti does anybody
know why we took a trip to master
chandra
kirti
to the crescent moon and not to the full
moon that's why we got off on master
chandra kirti mr famous as the moon in
the sky
okay well known as the moon in the sky
okay
and there was this comment that
what was the example of the station
market come on
no but what's the example is that when
you're
voting when you have voting cheetah the
buddhas will drive your cherry
yeah yeah when you have bodhichitta
the buddhists will drive your station
again so you can have fun with your
girlfriend in the back
and it's not an exaggeration that's what
the text said
okay yay sounds good
all right so where's oh
pal you got my ear boy up right i can't
tell
okay good all right so we were in the
subject of what is a listener
because chandi kirti decided
that at the very beginning of his book
the first thing he would say he would
talk about this idea
you know why are bodhisattvas more
important than
buddhas you know so he he bows down
he says buddhas are cool because they
are like
mothers who give birth
to two kinds of people listeners and
medium buddhas and
but then somebody in the next line they
say where do buddhists come from and he
says well
that's easy they come from bodhichitta
and the conversation continues okay
don't forget this book by of course
negotiates wisdom is important
but it's 27 cryptic
chapters of poetry it's impossible to
understand we're working on it nowadays
we're translating it and it's impossible
totally impossible so chandi kirti's
book which you are studying you have the
honor of studying
this week is the mother book of
all emptiness teachings in tibet in
china in korea
in japan all of the great mahayana
traditions
this is the this is the book this is the
most important book okay
so you should get used to it and you
should
dip into it once in a while okay that's
what we're doing
all right and it's a nice we're dipping
into
the first lines these are the opening
lines okay
and here we go so we finished one idea
one idea of what's a listener and
he said they listened to the perfect
teachings
they meditate on them and then they
reach the enlightenment
of the listeners
yeah the listeners and then they
help other people to hear them and
that's where the
so the listener is not only the
practitioner who hears it first
but they then they spread it by
getting others to hear it so they are
listeners in two cents
they they listen themselves but they
also cause other people to listen by
teaching it
later but it's all lower track okay
what makes it lower they didn't get
interested in
in the jumping planets like jumping
planets
all right good okay so here we go we're
continuing with that
and if i don't know if the tibetan
should be temper
okay cool thank you powell uh
so then there's a question
how do those guys teach okay how do
listeners
get other people to listen because
that's part of what their name
means they are listen listenizers
listenizers they get others to listen
okay
then uh zomkapa right he says
well how do they get other people to
listen and he says
it's very famous
now let's do the long version okay you
ready
here we go uh uh jack chamber
say that just repeat
[Music]
i will stop there it's too long this
this is a very famous sutra
that we use to take the one day mahayana
vows so it should have sounded familiar
okay this is a famous sutra that we
always use when we take our
one day vows and in the one day vows
we traditionally and don't forget
there's two kinds of one-day bells
one is mahayana and one is
not mahayana just normal
and so in the one-day vowel that's
focusing on
just general buddhism they make a big
deal
about if you practice this one day val
you will reach nirvana
okay there's not so much about
enlightenment okay
so they quote the sutra that says
here here's what it sounds like in
english i'm
i reach nirvana i'm a enemy destroyer
i wiped out all my impurities
i don't have any negative emotions
i've got power my mind is
liberated i know everything
i'm the great elephant i did what i had
to do
i do what i have to do okay very famous
and i have thrown off the geshe micro
backpack
of all the problems you know like i used
to have this crap
carrying around on my back now i'm free
okay
so when some copper asked the question
what do the listeners say to other
people he quotes that line
he quotes that he says oh they go around
saying i
did what i had to do you know i'm
finished
ciao corpora i dumped off the heavy
backpack
of my five heaps
okay of my five imperial heaps okay very
very famous
so if anybody ever asks you what's a
listener
you're going to say they listen to the
teachings but then they also
help others to listen well what do they
say to other people
challenge
i'm done man i'm out of here
okay it's like that all right that's
what they
help other people to listen to got it
all right
uh let's go back to our detour
uh oh and there should be a
a picture here of a guy yeah
he's like he's like saying
look i'm done this is this picture of a
guy
who's who's like look i'm finished i did
what i had to do
okay and wouldn't it be nice to say that
you know how do you feel this morning
i'm done man
what do you mean like i don't know i'm
never gonna be jealous again
i'm never gonna be angry again i'm done
it just happened this morning i'm so
happy
you know no more dental problems
i'm done okay
uh
she's gonna make him then this guy comes
up that's on kappa and says
that's not correct and he says
why not and he says you don't have our
hearts in the formless realm
he's like yeah you've got our hearts in
the formless realm
who's listening please to what
there's no sound in the formless man
okay
the guy's like i don't like this idea of
listener
what about the formless realm are there
arhats in the formless room or not yeah
there are some
well what do they do they can't listen
and they can't help other people to
listen there's no sound in the formless
room
then some kappa says child of the leg
for a hundred dollars cat
it's in the vagiogini practice but
what's its dance
what's it stand for i mean don't tell me
the second meaning tell me the
obvious
no but what's it represent what's the
word mean child of the link
it's a a lotus flower
yeah okay then that has a deeper meaning
that we can't talk about
okay so anyway uh
sao kappa says don't forget saroja
says born of the lake
which means the child of the lake we
translate it as child of the lake i like
it
and it means the lotus it means the
lotus flower
okay then he says
and the guy says what are you talking
about sanjay i i didn't ask you about
sanjay i was asking you about the
formless roman
nobody can talk there because there's no
sound and so kappa says
saruja and that's a
thousand dollar question if word was
here he might get it
but thank goodness he's not here
my life is much cheaper when he's not
here
uh what it means is uh
when we apply names sometimes
they are literal and sometimes there are
exceptions okay when you make a name
when you call somebody a name sometimes
it describes them
actually grown from the lake
but there are lotuses that grow on dry
land
there are kinds of lotuses that grow on
dry
in dry soil and not on the lake but we
still call them
born of the lake we still call them born
of the lake so tonkapa says look
we use words sometimes descriptively
and sometimes definitively okay and born
of the lake is
descriptive it's not definitive it's not
that every lotus in the universe has to
grow from a lake
but we like the word it's a cute word we
use it
why did he say that
yeah some listeners
do help other people to listen and some
listeners are in a realm where nobody
talks
but that doesn't mean we can't call them
listeners it's like
born of the leg got it it means there
are exceptions okay there are exceptions
but that doesn't mean we can't use the
word it's a cute word
it's a nice descriptive word even though
it's not
definitive okay cool
all right looming to jupa means
definitive
and that's a long story okay
and we're gonna show a lotus picture pal
is going to show a lotus picture
[Music]
i don't know if that's a subtle jar or
not but it is a subtle jar right
we can't see the water all right
first time i saw a real lotus
uh we we landed in bangalore in india
which is called the garden city of india
and all the
all the waste matter from the whole city
like 10 million people
is simply poured out into the ground
and it flows in a big river to the
west and there's a huge lake to the west
of the city
of pupu and you have to go through it to
get to sarah monastery
you have to drive through it and it's
unbelievable
but there's beautiful lotuses coming out
of there so
anyway then i i said stop the car i want
to get a lot of system no no no no
no no no anyway
okay
[Music]
then some kappa says let's look at the
sanskrit word
for listener and it will help us
appreciate
who these guys are okay uh which is
shravaka say shravaka
okay yeah i'm listening okay tedro
uh in tibetan it's it's two parts right
shrew and akka right
shru shru means to
listen or to hear and then
akka means hearer or doer
and the tibetans translated as
hearing and proclaiming hearing and
proclaiming
okay he says let's look at the sanskrit
nayang jupiter
let's understand listeners more
by looking at the sanskrit word for
listener
which literally means to proclaim what
you heard
they hear from the buddhas
the path to get to enlightenment they
study
they hear they listen
to the whole teaching of the whole
buddhist path
on how to get to highest enlightenment
okay they hear it they listen to it
don't forget there were two parts right
proclaim and listen listen and proclaim
is okay
listen and proclaim so so kappa says
look
we can understand more about these guys
if we look at the sanskrit
which is shrug
listen and proclaim okay and then he
says listen to what
they listen to the whole power from the
enlightened ones
then they akka they proclaim it
okay to whom to people who are
interested in the mahayana
to people who are interested in
bodhisattva
okay bodhichitta okay there's guys
called listeners
in sanskrit their name is listeners and
proclaimers
shrub akka and what do they do
they listen to the highest teachings
and then they can repeat them to people
who are
interested in the highest teachings okay
what's the implication
yeah they don't practice it themselves
okay so
so far we had guys who
who heard some stuff from the buna
enough to get to
nirvana and then corpora
they dumped their load okay
literally okay meaning they only reached
nirvana
that was the first explanation of
listener natsu kappa says hey
if you want to look at the sanskrit it's
deeper meaning
they can listen to all the buddhist
teachings
including bodhichitta teachings and they
can even teach them to other people
but they're not interested to practice
it themselves okay
and so listener becomes kind of a put
down
right derogatory in a way okay
all right
[Music]
now we're going to cover a whole subject
called
buddha buddha
and then some kappa says if you guys
understood
the idea called tatwa
buddha this whole thing we could clear
up this whole question
about who's getting born from who who's
a listener
and and what does it mean to be a medium
buddha and
is that a real buddha or is it not a
real buddha
because it's not a full buddha it's only
a half buddha
you can call them half buddhist okay
this whole question
about listeners half buddhists and full
buddhists
and full buddhas who want to drive the
station wagon
for the bodhisattva who wants to have
fun
okay you can understand everything
if you if you just understand tatwa
buddha okay
[Music]
yeah okay good tat means
that okay and tva
makes it into a abstract noun so tatwa
means suchness
thatness okay means such
nus okay tat means da or such
and then tua means tua is found in
english as t-i-o-n
locomotion election i know
all those sun verbs okay nouns okay
okay so tatwa means suchness which means
what
emptiness okay then what's buddha
it means to understand to grasp
something okay the literal meaning
of buddh buddha is to grasp and it came
into english for
twenty dollars
vid vid video
okay to see okay brood came into english
as
vid to see vision
wisdom with wiz comes from this comes
from bud
okay they all mean the same thing okay
then he says let's go that way okay
let's try to listen the idea of
tatwa buddha which means what now
to understand suchness okay
applies to this discussion listeners
let's call them half buddhas it's kind
of cool medium buddhist okay listeners
they what's their other name self-made
buddhist yeah
and and and total buddhist what do you
call
fully enlightened buddhists okay these
three guys
tatwa buddha applies to all of them and
if you understand
how they all understand suchness
then we can clear this whole thing up
about what parentage
what do you call that what's the other
fancy word for parentage
it comes up with the dna test for
kids paternity suits
yeah okay we can understand this whole
maternity paternity thing
if we understand tutva buddha okay
that's som kappa okay here we go
and then he turns to the lotus sutra
okay so you know it's such a famous
sutra and it's so beautiful
you know i was uh
not to digress which i never do
but the first job i ever had for my
teacher
was to be his driver and cook
for him to go to washington dc
for three months and learn english
so you know i had to drive him there and
i had to be his attendant
at a sinhalese
monastery they called vihara right
and we got there and they said who's
this uh
you know american guy
and he said this is my driver this is my
cook you know and they said he can't
stay here
he's not a monk you know at the time i
was in the moment so they said
he can't stay here and then my teacher's
like but i
you know i can't get to the school to
learn english if i don't have a driver
and they said tell them to go ask them
the guys across the street
you know and across the street there was
next to katherine graham's house
who owns the washington post uh
whose family owned the washington
there's a huge mansion
and it was the embassy of nigeria or
something
and some wealthy japanese businessman
bought it and he made a monastery
and there was one monk in the monastery
they said he has a 20 room house go ask
him if you can stay there
and then you can come across the street
when you need to cook you know
and i'm like okay and i went over there
and he didn't speak much english we
found a translator
he's this old japanese monk we figured
out he probably fought against my father
in the pacific
and uh so we're talking to each other
and
and he's i he said okay i understand
it's then you want to stay here
i said yeah he says okay
three o'clock nam-myoho-renge-kyo 3
o'clock
i'm like what's nam-myoho-renge-kyo
this is the lotus sutra these are the
first lines of the
lotus sutra if you recite with me
three hours of nam-myoho-renge-kyo every
morning
at three you can stay here you have to
beat the drum
and i'm like oh my god you know
and so i said i'm sorry i have to ask my
teacher he said
ask your teacher no nam you're gonna get
girl no sleep
here so i went to
rinpoche you know he said he he says i
can stay there he says good good
but he says i have to get up at three
o'clock and we stay home
slow the sutra for three hours and bang
on the drum
she says do it i said
well what am i supposed to think about
while i'm doing that he said
review the lam ram in your head you know
just forget what you're saying and
just go through the long rim in your
head and bang the drum you know
every time you bang the drum think of
the next part of the alum room
and i'm like okay that's cool and so i
did it
and uh and everything went very
uh what do you call it we didn't fit
but we worked together we and we worked
together and
one day i was up way up in a tree and he
was holding the ladder
and the branch came down i was supposed
to cut the tree
and then he ran away and with the ladder
and i was like dude and then after that
we became really close friends
and then one day he said
okay you keep the monastery i'm leaving
and i'm like what he says you keep this
mansion you can have it
you know i'm leaving you know and i'm
like
where are you going he said i decided
america needs
nam myoho renge kyo and i'm gonna walk
to los angeles
with my drum and he did
he walked to los angeles and back with
his drum
and he did nam-myoho-rengenko but i had
a choice of being with my teacher or
having this mansion
and i decided to stick with my teacher
luckily for you guys okay
okay guest lock can you get back to the
subject
lotus sutra so kappa says we can use the
lotus sutra here
okay and by the way there's two lotus
sutras and that's a long story
um he says in the lotus sutra which is
called the white lotus sutra
it says gumbo telling dr
dampa yandapaki
this is the buddha's disciples
talking to the buddha gumbo o protector
tearing into gear today we became your
listeners
this is where the whole listener thing
comes from is the lotus sutra
okay so in the lord sutra the buddhist
students
say to the buddha oh buddha we're so
happy today we became your listeners
okay and then they say what's a listener
chandra damba yanda pagi we will
proclaim
this highest enlightenment in the world
you know probably we'll go out with our
drama and nam yoho and
give it to san francisco or l.a you know
by the way it's a beautiful practice and
i think it did help the united states
uh so anyway uh
we we promise to spread
this highest teachings of in the
teachings of highest enlightenment okay
then they say uh we will tell everybody
about this enlightenment did you hear a
change in them in the sentence
in the second line we will spread this
highest enlightenment
in the third line we will tell everybody
about enlightenment
they don't mention highest
okay in the second line they say we have
learned from you
about highest enlightenment now we will
tell everybody about this enlightenment
okay
it's important okay last line day weight
doctor
mesendra therefore from now on
you can call us your listeners
okay therefore from now on buddha
you can call your students your
listeners
why two reasons we
listen to your teachings and we help
others to hear them we proclaim them
okay got it this is where the whole word
came from from the lotus sutra okay cool
now you are listener experts those who
are listening
if it ever comes up now you know where
it came from
now there's a problem with the verse
there's a famous problem with the verse
okay
and someday maybe tim can translate the
lotus to that that's
it's pretty common you're going to do
something else
you're going to do charlie llama's
channels i think
uh anyway
there's a famous problem about this
highest part
you know do they listen to the highest
enlightenment and do they spread the
highest enlightenment
that's a question okay here here we go
um
and i have a picture pile of somebody
proclaiming something okay
this is i don't know i always think of
this picture
this guy is going hey everybody you know
there's a lot of ram going on in diamond
mountain you know
this is tim trying to find people to
come to learn hey
okay okay good
all right
so really this
quotation is the ultimate source
of the idea of a listener and his
two jobs or her two jobs one listen to
the teachings
two help other people to hear them
proclaim them spread them okay shrub
akka
okay all right
[Music]
this is where it all comes from what's
that mean
tim kaichi
yeah the other guy now somebody whenever
you see the word kachik
someone's going to cause a problem okay
it's like it died mountain and somebody
says uh
about my room they're like oh no what's
wrong with your room
yeah i don't know i got a i got a
javelina who
lives in the bathroom or something wild
pig
okay
now akachi comes and tries to cause some
trouble
he says did you notice that in the third
line
it's missing the word highest
therefore uh when these guys
listen they listen to the highest
teachings
but when they proclaim them they only
proclaim the lower teachings
okay he says that's not my position
that's your slow the sutra socapa
okay he says that's you chose the wrong
sutra
it's obvious these guys don't proclaim
the
highest teachings okay
yeah yeah you can say that but it's
wrong okay some compasses you're wrong
why
dabuni taichenki yeah the first
enlightenment the highest enlightenment
does refer to bodhichitta enlightenment
right
the one you're given but the second one
they just left out the word highest
because they wanted to emphasize
that it was the vehicle it was the way
to get to the teachings
so they didn't repeat highest okay
that since some covers like don't give
me don't hassle me
all right they did listen to the highest
teachings
including bodhichitta and they do pass
them on
even though they may not practice them
okay good chances
says a question may come up in your
minds
our bodhisattvas listeners or not
in this sense is a bodhisattva listener
don't forget we have three levels of
practitioner
what listeners medium buddhist half
buddhas
and full buddhists okay so these are the
bodhisattva guys up here
and some compass says how about we
collapse it to two kinds
why because aren't the bodhisattvas
listeners
in this idea in the lotus sutra way
don't they learn the highest teachings
don't they pass them on to other people
don't they fit the lotus sutra let's
collapse it to two paths
okay so kappa is proposing right okay
yeah you're right but just no problem
yeah you're right
what are they right bodhisattvas do
listen to the highest teachings
and they do proclaim them to other
people but that don't make them
listeners
that don't make them lowest track okay
because
lowest track means they hear it
they teach it but they don't practice it
and that doesn't apply to bodhisattvas
got it
you're never going to forget now about
listeners okay uh
good uh
yeah they don't practice it ranking mean
duper means they don't practice it
themselves okay
the other listeners so it doesn't apply
to bodhisattvas
all right and
the picture is a lady
why did i choose this picture she's
covering her ears
yeah she's not a yeah good she's a funny
sampler
because she's not listening to the lower
path okay got it
she's not listening to the lower
presentation no no
hey just take care of yourself richard
nirvana
you know just dump your loan and she's
like what
who's she she's a buddy supper
don't don't tell me about this personal
nirvana thing i'm not interested
i want to help everybody okay don't tell
me about making myself happy
that's not happiness happiness is making
everybody happy
including me okay all right um
now tonka has covered
listener guess where he's going next
yeah what's a half buddha what the heck
what the heck
is mine
they have the buddhist mind yeah what
does it mean to be a
a half buddha that's a weird word you
know
hey what are you i'm a half burner oh is
it the upper half of the lore huh
i don't know if you're gonna ride this
thing in in our room in the next room
over here you better have the lower half
and that's an inside if you want to know
that joke you have to come to thai mama
okay so now some coffee is gonna cover
half buddhas okay what the heck is a
half buddha all right
why are we covering half buddha because
chanda kirti mentioned it
why did chanda kirti mention it he was
talking about
two kinds of practitioners who are born
from the womb
of full buddhists why did he talk about
that
because he wanted you to get in the mood
of asking what
womb do people come from
because he's gonna get to how full
buddhas
come from the womb of bodhisattvas
crescent moons and not full moons
so we better respect the we better drive
their station wagon
got it yay all right sangeet jing ship a
sanghini
then some cop says what the heck is this
self-made
buddha what's a half buddha okay
in the commentary which means
chad kirti's commentary to his own book
there's a famous
long auto commentary
to enter in the middle way okay so the
most famous
book the book which triggered the
emptiness teachings of
all of asia all of north ay the mahayana
countries
the book which triggered that has its
own explanation
and it's big and it's difficult okay
and nobody works with it because it's
too difficult okay
that's why you need some couple in the
commentary he says
sange
buddhahood enlightenment can apply to
all three
the idea of enlightenment can apply to
listeners have an enlightenment half
buddhas have an enlightenment
self-made buddhist and full buddhas have
an enlightenment there's three
enlightenments going on here
there's three enlightenments going on
here so in that sense
they are all buddha okay
that's why a half buddha can be a buddha
because they do have some kind of
enlightenment
they do understand they are enlightened
about something there's three
enlightenments going on here
three what's the sanskrit
tatwa buddhas there's three buddhas
going on here
what tatva buddhas they're all
enlightened
about tatwa what's tatwa
if you are enlightened about suchness
are you necessarily fully enlightened
no good we're on the right track all
right here we go
gets us to where we were trying to get
today and we're doing good tim i think
we're going to make it
talk about buddha okay now he says this
is where tatwa buddha comes up
okay this is where enlightened
about suchness comes up okay three kinds
of enlightenment
about suchness and why can we call a
half buddha
a buddha it's not because they're a
buddha
it's because they buddha
they get it they boot
so they're buddhists but they're not
real buddhist got it
they booed but they're not buddha okay
what's good mean they get it okay
what cutback okay suchness
if you see emptiness directly do you
have to be a buddha
no no but are you a tatwa
buddha yeah because that buddha means
you understand it you get it you saw it
okay so here's some couple kachi
what's that yeah i like it
some copper says i like it some people
go to tata buddha here
to explain this this problem about three
levels
he says lekso i like it
when when tokapa says i like it it's
damn good
okay it means i think it's damn good i
love this type of buddha thing
okay and then he goes to explain the
word
tatwa buddha okay and he says what's
tatwa
konani
means just that and he means nas
this just darkness is the
tibetan translation of tatwa just
that-ness
it means emptiness okay it means
emptiness
he says tatwa means just that nas
buddha means kong the chipper kondacipa
means
fully grasp fully to really get it to
really get it okay
okay 10 day what's the point
the point is that all three levels
have tatva buddha why they all saw
emptiness directly okay which proves you
don't have to be a what to do what you
shouldn't wait till i offer some money
uh anyway she just gives her away in 10
minutes later
uh yeah okay
so uh they need to be wrong
so everybody even
half buddhists are tupper buddha
okay are they buddhas no are they tough
for buddha
yeah good yay sangeeth
by the way but they will become buddhas
because they tap a buddha
if you're tatwa buddha you're halfway
there okay if you see emptiness directly
you're halfway to becoming a real buddha
okay all right cheer buddha
and then it's a beautiful sentence uh
it's
this book uh so kappa's ultimate work on
emptiness
you know uh gomba rapso
elimination of what is it
of the truth on you gotta let me finish
it
you guys gotta let me finish it okay
please let me finish it don't put all
this
okay uh
if you just anyway i'm not going to
complain all right
he says generally the word buddha
means enlightened being but what's he
going to say cup
cup deer mitsamo but it don't
fit the context here mitsamo sam means a
retreat border right but if you spell it
a little
differently it means to fit the occasion
so he says enlightened being doesn't
quite fit here
because you should understand that the
word buddha
has two other meanings the word buddha
has two other important beautiful
meanings
okay and it's very beautiful you know
it's so beautiful to know what the word
buddha means
which if you send me emails about how
irritated you are at your closest
friends
i won't have time to translate it do you
understand what i'm saying you guys
all right any personal problem you're
having
my advice is wait six months
they'll die you'll die
things will change okay it's easy
this is from an old man you know just
wait six months wait six years you can't
remember their name
so just chill out go back to your
meditation
don't worry about irritating people okay
anyway that's my universal email
response
uh buddha johnny he says here's the two
meanings
of buddha the word buddha special
meaning special meaning
number one what's a badma
a lotus the opening of the of the
petals is called buddha
okay the opening of a lotus petals is
called buddha
okay that's the other meaning of the
root buddh
it means okay cool
or nice means to wake up
from a deep sleep okay
means the lotus opens
the snorer wakes up wakes themselves up
probably
okay that's a self-made buddha
we got it the secret transmission
he says don't think
that the word buddha has to apply
to a foley mind being it doesn't it can
mean an opening of a lotus
it can mean someone waking up it can
mean someone suddenly understanding
something
and by the way at that point he quotes a
very difficult
book of sanskrit that was translated
into tibetan okay
and we spent quite a while getting that
we have some other picture here
paul some lady waking up
yeah i like this lady okay she's buddha
okay this lady is buddha she just got up
she just woke up okay all right
uh now sam kappa says what do you think
he's we
we have a principle in the mixed nuts
translation team which is
very important for translators okay
and and you you close your eyes and you
ask yourself
what's next if i'm tonka
i covered listener i
covered half of
half buddha what's next
what do they do
i'll say it again it's a pun
i covered half of half buddha
i covered the buddha part what's the
other one
yeah what's the other half which is half
no it's half got it
the other half he didn't talk about yet
is half
okay half buddha so she said i covered
the buddha you got it you guys
wake up flower opening doesn't have to
mean
enlightened being can mean understand
emptiness directly
these guys do understand emptiness
directly that's how they get to the
throwing off their load okay but what
the heck is half
why do you say half buddha okay so
naturally he's gonna talk about that
okay that's called
ding say ding
there's another famous ding in the alarm
rim for fifty dollars
yeah good medium length long room
but there's also by the way you got 25
dollars okay
and there's also keyboarding jing people
jing people what's that mean in the long
rim
what is a medium person yeah medium
capacity yay that you got the 25
and you got the 25 okay
but this is the word that tonka uses for
half buddha
ding you know the middle one
okay here's the listeners here's the
full buddhist
and here's the self-made buddhist
halfway to
halfway to full buddha okay halfway
buddha okay
what separates now here's the big
question
what separates these guys from these
guys
here's geshe-la's fingers okay what
separates
here's listeners proclaimers right
and here's half buddhist and here's
full buddhist what's the difference
between these two guys
uh it is but the classic answer okay
these guys have a hundred cowboys of
practice on these guys
these guys have a hundred kalpas of
practice
are these guys these guys have been at
diamond mountain
for a hundred kelpers these guys just
got there
okay this is cat cutting
okay and i don't know these are those
babies who are showing up nowadays
great babies we got great babies coming
to dime mountain we got
we got beautiful young people
volunteering here so anyway
next generation right so how long is a
kalpa i once worked on it for like a
week
and no answer sorry and you won't find
one in the scriptures
they will say call it 500 billion years
or something
okay i don't know 500 million years
okay these guys have a hundred campus on
these guys
so don't complain if you have to
practice another month
how do you get to how do you graduate
from being a listener to being a half
buddha
it's simple stonecarpet says look it's
simple
you just have to practice a couple
billion more years
okay and then you get here by the way
that's what makes tantra so attractive
right
you don't have to do these billions of
years stuff in one lifetime
with a practice like medicine buddha
tara
baja yogini especially you can
reach full enlightenment you could save
all that time okay
why is it important to save time
people are hurting people are hurting
every moment you delay
someone's getting hurt someone's
brother's dying
somebody's got cancer every day you
waste someone's getting hurt okay who
didn't have to get hurt all right
don't feel guilty but you should okay
all right so uh going to pay kapaki
so that's the main difference now
thousand dollars oh my god we got
four minutes left thousand dollars
some people try to say the difference is
different
it's not how much time in the difference
between a listener
and a self-made buddha okay some people
say
that's not the difference some people
say differently
tim might know some people want to say
there's a different difference between
these first two guys
nope
yay nobody got it
uh some people say they see a different
emptiness
okay some people say they see a
different
degree of emptiness and then the lower
middleway school the main reason it
exists
is to describe the degrees of emptiness
okay like like
level one emptiness and level two
emptiness
and level three emptiness like that they
wanna have different kinds of emptiness
they want to have different degrees of
difficulty
emptiness okay and that's where you
start getting into the mind only school
emptiness
you know and all kinds of things like
that
every buddhist school has a different
idea
about degrees of emptiness you know
deeper emptinesses
than other emptinesses and just because
we're gonna
end the class pretty soon what's the
highest quote say about that
no difference if you see it once
if if you're on
a listener track and you couldn't care
less about
jumping planets and you just want to
save yourself
and you don't care about other people
but you see
emptiness you have seen the exact same
emptiness
that the buddha is looking at now
there's no
there's no difference between
how a fully enlightened buddha sees
emptiness
and how a selfish person a physicist
who has an insight into emptiness sees
it
there's no difference what they see is
the same thing
that's amazing okay the mind seeing it
is different full of compassion or full
of
wanting to publish a good paper but
what they understand is has no
difference at all okay if a physicist
understands emptiness which many are
close to
i think or or a buddha understands
emptiness
or you or you see emptiness today
that's exactly the same emptiness that
the buddhists are seeing
and you see it as much as they do they
don't see it any more than you do
you see it a hundred percent and they
see it a hundred percent
because there's no degrees of emptiness
okay
does your kitchen have mice
yeah if your kitchen has a mouth right
then what do you want to do yeah you
want to get him out of the kitchen
okay this is important okay i'm not
kidding okay
uh so
either there's mice in your kitchen or
there's no mice
in your kitchen it's very simple okay
now some kids in the monastery
the irritating seven-year-olds who sneak
into the debate ground
and there are such things they sneak
into the baby
i'm in at the mouth it's got his nose in
the kitchen but his butt is outside of
the kitchen
like you can imagine that mouse is
halfway into the kitchen right
then then it's not the master's in the
kitchen it's not the most it's not in
the kitchen the mouth is kind of in the
kitchen and ralph's kind of not in the
kitchen
then we say no we reject this okay
either
the kitchen is mouthless or it's not
it cannot be semi-mouthless
the whole idea of the mouse's nose in
the in being in the kitchen and the
butt's outside the door
is false okay in that case you have a
mouth in your kitchen
okay if his butt's in the kitchen he'll
poop in the kitchen and you'll know
okay so either the mouse is in the
kitchen and the mouse is outside the
kitchen there's only two states it's
like
a binary on computer code either zero or
one there's no point five
in computer code computers don't work on
point fives either zero or one switched
on switched off
why we talked about that
either you see pure emptiness or you
didn't see emptiness and there's nothing
in between
got it either the mouse is not in the
kitchen
or the mouse is in the kitchen and
there's no degrees
of mouse in the kitchen there's no
degrees the emptiness
that you see on the first day you see
emptiness
and the and the the depth to which you
see it
buddha buddha is no different
from how the buddha is seeing it right
now they're completely the same
in that sense you are a complete buddha
at that moment that you see emptiness
directly you are tatwa buddha okay got
it
yay